In this race, there are no drivers.
这场赛事中 没有司机
No human behind the wheel.
方向盘无人操控
These robots are on their own.
机器人必须独立驾驶
Their human observers can't even keep up.
人类观察者甚至追不上它们
It's literally outrunning us.
这真的超过我们了
I don't know you can do it with this car. I can't keep up with this.
我没想到它们居然开得这么好 我都跟不上了
It's the first race ever where the machine makes all the decisions.
这是史上第一场由机器做出全部决定的比赛
Think of it as a technology demonstration.
你可以把它看作一场技术演示
It'll turn believers out of the nonbelievers.
那些不相信技术的最终会被技术所折服
Behind each robot is a team of people,
在每台机器人的背后都是一个团队
who sacrificed everything creating hardware
他们牺牲了一切 他们所开发的硬件和软件
and software to attempt what's never been done before.
将尝试一项前所未有的壮举
If they put the blood,
这些车辆中
sweat, and tears into your vehicle to make it there.
凝聚了人们的心血、汗水和泪水
I work 16 hour days.
连续好几个月
Seven days a week for months on end.
我每周工作 7 天 每天 16 个小时
The people that fell into this project get consumed by it.
参加这个项目的所有人 全部殚精竭虑
I even dream about it.
我做梦都会在做项目
Dreams will now be put to the test.
如今 梦想即将接受考验
It's winner take all with a $2 million prize,
获胜者将独得 200 万美元大奖
but the stakes are much higher.
但风险要高得多
Can a machine navigate miles of punishing desert terrain.
在复杂的沙漠地形中 机器能否行驶数英里
The speed and agility of a human driver.
并且速度和灵敏性不输人类驾驶员？
Find out. The race begins, on NOVA.
让我们拭目以待 这场比赛是由 NOVA 发起的
California Speedway, Mecca for NASCAR auto racing.
加州高速公路是美国纳斯卡车赛的圣地
In October of 2005,
2005 年 10 月
43 teams have brought their vehicles to compete in a unique event.
43 支团队携带他们的车辆 参加了一项独特的赛事
A race driven not by testosterone, but computer code.
一项由计算机代码驾驶 而非人类驾驶的比赛
These machines are robots,
这些机器是机器人
and they're going to run an obstacle course with
它们将开车通过一条越野障碍赛道
no one behind the wheel and no remote control.
没有人工操作方向盘 没有远程遥控
It's called the Grand Challenge.
这场比赛叫机器人挑战大赛
And for good reason, on a two mile course,
原因很简单 赛道长两英里
these robots are on their own and there's plenty to trip them up.
障碍重重 机器人必须独立驾驶
They'll encounter gates and tunnels and all kinds of obstacles including,
它们将穿越大门 隧道和各种障碍物
parked cars and hay bales.
包括静止车辆和干草捆
The competition comes in all shapes and sizes.
参赛机器人形状和大小各异
The smallest robot is Ghostrider.
最小的机器人叫 Ghostrider
Ladies and gentlemen, the world's first autonomous motorcycle,
女士们 先生们 世界第一台自动摩托车
Ghostrider approaching obstacle one.
Ghostrider 正在接近第一个障碍
As though raised from the dead.
Ghosrider 死而复生
Ghostrider bravery forges on.
勇敢前进
Now, the largest entry,
现在  体型最大的选手入场
a 16-ton truck called TerraMax approaches the first gate and hesitates.
一辆 16 吨重的卡车 名为 TerraMax 它在第一扇门前停下了
Come on baby, crank it, crank it, crank it.
继续 动啊 动啊 动啊
Do it, do it,
加油 加油
do it, do it, no.
加油 加油 不要
Like anxious parents, its creators look on in agony,
它的发明者如同焦急的父母 满脸焦虑
but all they can do is watch as TerraMax backs up and tries again.
TerraMax 后退 再次尝试 他们只能焦急地旁观
It's like a bull in a China shop. Come on.
它就像一头瓷器店里的公牛 加油
On the eighth pass,
第八次尝试
TerraMax squeezes through the gate and heads for the finish.
TerraMax 穿过了大门 冲向终点
Tommy has a lovable retro appearance,
Tommy 有着可爱的复古风格外观
but looks are a bit deceiving.
但它的内心却并非如此
A computer glitch turns the robot into a wild beast.
由于电脑故障 它变成了狂野巨兽
There are no serious injuries but
没有造成严重的人员伤害
Tommy is out of the competition.
但 Tommy 出局了
Team DAD has arrived from Silicon Valley with
Team DAD 来自硅谷 它的车顶装饰看上去
a roof ornament that looks like a relic from an old disco.
颇具古旧的迪斯科遗风
It's a homemade laser scanner,
它实际上是自制的激光扫描器
created by Dave Hall and his brother Bruce.
由 Dave Hall 和 Bruce 兄弟俩制造
Even as they drive to the start,
就在车辆开到起点时
they're writing computer code to make their scanner work.
他们仍在写扫描器的计算机代码
Now, it's show time.
现在 表演时刻到了
We want to watch the first one ready now. Which one's up?
现在 请第一位参赛者准备就绪 谁先来？
Almost immediately, they hit the hay.
话音未落 车辆撞到了干草堆上
For this run, Team DAD,
第一次尝试 颇具 70 年代迪斯科风格
like disco in the 70's, is dead.
的 Team DAD 熄火了
But they'll have another chance.
但是他们还有一次机会
Many universities are fielding teams and Stanley, Stanford's robot,
很多大学都组建了比赛团队 斯坦福大学的机器人 Stanley
looks like a high-tech version of another VW Herbie, The Love Bug.
看起来就像是是大众甲壳虫的高科技版本
Stanley is the brainchild of Sebastian Thrun.
Stanley 的构思者是 Sebastian Thrun
For him the Grand Challenge is a Woodstock for Robo-Geeks.
对他来说 这场机器人挑战大赛对机器人极客而言 就像音乐圈的伍德斯托克音乐节
There's very little in the way of competitiveness.
实际上并不存在什么竞争
Although everybody understands, in the end of a day, everyone wants to win.
尽管大家都知道 所有人都想赢
Its been a big fest, it's like a thousand people who care about the same thing.
实际上 这是一场盛会 千余名观众关注的是同一件事情
Making cars drive themselves and they all get together.
他们聚集在此 是为了见证无人驾驶车的梦想成真
It's a big festival. It's really great.
这是一场盛大的节日 这太棒了
The largest team at the competition is from Carnegie Mellon in Pittsburgh.
这次竞赛最大的团队是来自匹兹堡的卡内基梅隆大学
And for them the Grand Challenge is no love fest.
对它们而言 这次机器人挑战大赛是一场严肃的考验
But you're either, thoroughly rested, 200% effectiveness or you've got some work to do.
大家已经休息好了 接下来 希望你们打起精神 迎接下面的比赛
No one knows what it takes to succeed in the Grand Challenge,
没有人知道要赢得机器人挑战大赛需要付出多少
since no one anywhere has done it.
因为还没有人赢过
The Red Team is prepared for anything.
Red 的团队已经准备好面对一切
Led by former Marine, Red Whittaker,
Red 的团队的领队是前海军陆战队员 Red Whittaker
the Red Team is a well-funded army of computer wizards and engineers.
他们资金充裕 都是电脑和工程师奇才
The team has invested two years and
他们花了两年的时间
millions of dollars to get Sandstorm to the starting line.
还有数百万美元 最终才让 Sandstorm 来到了起跑线
Ladies and gentlemen, from Pittsburgh, PH.
女士们 先生们 让我们欢迎来自宾夕法尼亚州匹兹堡的团队
This is a nice angle for the approach, get crisp, get crisp,
这个入场的角度很好 小心 小心
get crisp. Dang, beautiful.
小心 太漂亮了
Sandstorm is aggressive on the straight away.
Sandstorm 正在全速直线前进
But today, the robot has a fatal attraction to hay bales.
但是今天 这台机器人似乎被干草堆迷住了
Like all the entries,
和其他选手一样
Sandstorm has four chances to demonstrate agility and speed for the judges.
Sandstorm 有四次机会向裁判展示它的灵巧和速度
Based on their performance,
根据它们的表现
20 robots will qualify for the main event,
会有 20 台机器人进入正赛
a long distance desert race and a chance to win $2 million.
正赛为长距离沙漠赛道 有机会赢取 200 万美元奖金
The race is sponsored by DARPA,
比赛由 DARPA 赞助
the Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency.
其全称为国防高等研究计划署
Their goal is to stimulate technology that can be used by the military.
赞助目标是促进可以用于军队的技术研发
If we can use unmanned vehicles,
如果在危险任务中可以使用无人驾驶车
in dangerous missions like delivering supplies to frontlines.
例如前线给养运送
Then we can take drivers out of the vehicles and they're less vulnerable.
我们就可以省去驾驶员 并且提升可靠性
If you remember Private Jessica Lynch,
不知道大家是否还记得 Jessica Lynch 列兵的惨剧
she was a driver of a supply vehicle.
她是一名给养车驾驶员
And if that was an autonomous vehicle that episode would've never happened.
如果是无人驾驶车 那这场惨剧完全可以避免
True Autonomy, that's what we're after. It's a hard problem.
真正的无人驾驶 这是我们的目标 这是个艰难的挑战
Just how hard a problem it
开发一台无人驾驶车到底有多困难
is to create a vehicle that can drive itself became painfully clear a year earlier,
一年前的机器人挑战大赛
at the first Grand Challenge Race.
已经给出了足够的证明
Carnegie Mellon was one of 15 teams at the starting line.
在起点上有 15 支团队 卡内基梅隆大学是其中之一
Racing against the clock,
它们争分夺秒
Sandstorm was the first robot out of the gate.
Sandstorm 是第一台出发的机器人
To win, it had to run a course across 142 miles
要赢得比赛 它必须在 10 小时之内穿越 142
of rugged desert terrain in less than 10 hours.
英里的崎岖沙漠赛道
But just seven miles from the start Sandstorm drifted off course and got stuck on a rock.
但刚行驶了 7 英里 Sandstorm 就偏离了赛道 卡在了一块岩石上
In a valiant effort to keep moving,
它义无反顾 尝试着前进
the robot spun its wheels until its tires burst into flame.
车轮狂转 直到轮胎起火
Back at the start,
在它后面的起点线上
other robots were having their own problems.
其他机器人也都出现了问题
Everything was set up for this high-speed rumble,
大家都以为万事俱备 这些车辆可以从容应对
of all these vehicles just careening through the desert.
高速冲过这条沙漠赛道
And that's not what happened.
而真实情况并非如此
All 15 robots died of mechanical failure,
所有 15 台机器人都碰到了机械故障 停了下来
half within the first mile.
其中一半没跑过半英里
In this group of losers,
在这组失败者中
Sandstorm went the farthest.
Sandstorm 是跑得最远的
Leading many to believe no robot could ever win the Grand Challenge.
人们开始相信 机器人不可能赢得这场挑战
The fact that the vehicles only travel short distance,
看到车辆只跑了这么短的距离
shows that it was a tough technical problem,
人们明白了这个技术难题的难度
but where the success really lies in
但真正让我们取得成功的
the amount of people that actually responded to the challenge.
是对这次挑战作出回应的人数
After this fiasco, Carnegie Mellon now has a year to prepare for the next race.
这次惨败后 卡耐基梅隆大学有一年的时间准备下一次比赛
Let's settle in. Go to work.
大家好 各就各位 准备开工
The five main things that we said that we would get done for today, aren't done.
之前说了今天要做的五项任务 必须完成
So, it's not enough to wave hands and say, voila, this works.
我不想看到大家挥挥手 然后说 瞧 这样可以 都动起来了
I signed up to succeed the Grand Challenge.
我报名参加机器人挑战大赛 就是为了赢
This time around, the Red Team will be more like a Red Army.
这次 Red 的团队会更像一支军队
It is a machine to be reckoned with.
我们的对手是机器
Red Whittaker's resume is a veritable history of field robotics.
Red Whittaker 的个人履历 都和名副其实的野地机器人相关
His robots are battle hardened machines
他的机器人都是战场专用的机器
built to clean up Three Mile Island and Chernobyl.
曾在三里岛核电站和切尔诺贝利的清理中大展身手
These rust belt brutes can map dangerous mines,
这些履带生锈的家伙们能够测绘矿藏、给卡车装货
load trucks, remove asbestos, and mow hay.
拆除防火石棉或者割草
They're global explorers that have ventured across volcanoes, deserts, and glaciers.
它们的足迹遍布全球 包括火山、沙漠和冰川
Now, Whittaker has staked his reputation on winning the Grand Challenge.
现在 为了赢得机器人挑战大赛 Whittaker 赌上了他的名声
To double his chances,
为了让获胜几率加倍
he's planning to run two robots in the next race.
他准备在下次比赛中派出两台机器人
In addition to their veteran, Sandstorm,
除了经验丰富的 Sandstorm
the Red Team will transform this new Hummer into
Red 的团队还准备把新机器人
a more aggressive machine called Highlander.
Hummer 改造成更激进的机器 并改名为 Highlander
For more than a year,
在一年多的时间里
Wayt Gibbs has been documenting Whittaker's Grand Challenge quest.
Wait Gibbs 一直在记录 Whittaker 为机器人挑战大赛付出的努力
Red Whittaker is nothing,
Red Whittaker 一直充满了
if not an ambitious man.
雄心壮志
He's a roboticist too,
他也是一名机器人学家
in his weekends goes out and drives a tractor for 10 hours on his farm.
周末的时候 他会在自己的农场开上 10 个小时的拖拉机
And who likes to actually get in and get his hands greasy and dirty inside an engine.
他喜欢动手探索 为了研究发动机内部 他愿意搞得自己满手油污
Red gets excited about seeing his robots do powerful things in the real world.
看到他自己的机器人在真实世界大展身手 他就会兴奋
It's going work. The thing,
我感觉这次能成 目前这个阶段
with this stage of the game its making it,
我们的目标是 开始改造
making it work great make it work.
让它能够开动起来
You take that off.
打开引擎盖
The Red Team will spend several months replacing and modifying Highlander's hardware.
Red 的团队需要花几个月 替换并修改 Highlander 的硬件
A tremendous amount of these desert racing machines is heavy metal, iron mongering.
这些沙漠赛车需要大量重金属 钢铁框架
It's heating and beating and bashing and cutting, and making.
需要加热、锻造、敲打、成型
It's as important as any of the software. And it's a lot of fun.
这和软件同样重要 这非常有趣
To replace the human behind the wheel,
为了取代方向盘前的驾驶员
team members have installed an electromechanical system to steer,
团队成员安装了一个电子机械系统 负责转向
shift, throttle, and brake.
换挡、油门和刹车
They're installing sensors, so Highlander can see.
他们安装了传感器 让车辆具备视觉
And GPS receivers, so it can follow the racecourse.
还安装了 GPS 接收器 让车辆可以感知赛道
And they're giving the robot a break and
他们还给机器人安装了一个大脑
filling it with software so it can drive by itself.
里面安装了软件 这样它就可以自动驾驶了
Now, it might seem easy for robots to drive.
让机器人开车似乎并不困难
It happens all the time in the movies.
电影里随处可见
I'll drive.
我来开车
If you think of the Terminator movies,
你会想到电影《终结者》系列
science-fiction has given us a really distorted view of the capabilities of robots.
科幻小说中 机器人具备各种酷炫能力
Those robots are able to identify specific individuals.
他们可以识别个人身份
But in reality, robots have very limited senses of perception.
但在现实中 机器人的感知能力相当有限
Robots know nothing about their environment and they can't think like humans.
机器人对周边环境一无所知 它们不能像人一样思考
But they're really good at crunching numbers.
但他们非常善于数字计算
Most rely on laser rangefinders to perceive the world.
大多数机器人都依赖于激光测距仪来感知世界
Inside, a beam of light bounces off a spinning mirror and sweeps the terrain ahead.
在一束光内 有一个旋转的镜子 持续扫描前面的地面
By measuring the time it takes a beam to hit something and return,
通过测量光束到达目标和返回
the range finder can measure its distance from the vehicle.
所需的时间 测距仪可以测量目标和车辆的距离
Scanners are mounted in pairs to measure different things.
扫描器成对安装 以测量不同物体
Some look for smooth road ahead,
有的扫描器测量前面的光滑路面
others look for the road edge on each side.
其他则测量两侧的路缘
Some look for vertical objects - a rock or a fence post that can kill a robot.
有些扫描器寻找垂直物体 如可能伤害机器人的岩石或篱笆
Putting it all together,
所有扫描器一起
this becomes Highlander's view of the world - A road map made from millions of
帮助 Highlander 观察世界 - 由数百万个数字构成的道路地图
numbers that basically tells the robot bumpy or smooth.
可以告诉机器人道路是颠簸还是平坦的
Off on its own,
开始出发
Highlander will try to avoid obstacles for the first time.
Highlander 将第一次尝试自行避开障碍物
Improving its driving skills will take endless hours of programming.
要改进它的驾驶技能 需要无数个小时的编程
The Red Team robots have on the order of a million lines of computer code.
Red 的团队机器人编写了一百万行计算机代码
Even so, they do very simple reasoning about the world.
即便如此 机器人仍然只能对世界进行简单的推理
They look for flat spots. Flat is good.
它们会寻找平坦地面 平坦的就是好的
Drive on flat spots.
它会在平坦地面驾驶
Anything that's not flat, avoid it.
它们会避开任何不平坦的地方
But for the Red Team,
但对 Red 的团队来说
winning the Grand Challenge involves much more than writing computer code.
要赢得机器人挑战大赛 他们需要的不仅仅是写代码
While some team members are testing Highlander in the field,
一些团队成员正在现场测试 Highlander
others are refurbishing Sandstorm.
其他人则在重新改造 Sandstorm
Another group is building state of the art sensors.
另一组正在打造顶级传感器
And writing software never ends.
并且永不停歇地编写软件
Whittaker commands an army of 100 or more with a $3 million war chest.
Whittaker 领导着 100 多人的团队 有 300 万美元资金
He's determined to have two robots at the starting line and one in the winner's circle.
他决心让两台机器人全部参赛 其中一台一定要赢
A lot of people work hard.
很多人都在努力
Red Team's no exception on that front.
Red 的团队也不例外
Winning a race isn't about working hard.
赢得比赛 不单需要努力
Yeah, you got to do that. But it's a lot more.
是的 你必须努力 但还有其他因素
If you haven't done everything, you haven't done a thing.
如果不全盘考虑 就会全盘皆输
Not all teams take Whittaker's all or nothing approach.
并不是所有团队都像 Whittaker 团队一样破釜沉舟
For the Hall brothers, the Grand Challenge is great fun.
对于 Hall 兄弟俩 机器人挑战大赛充满了乐趣
Each day, Bruce and Dave program their robot as they drive into work.
每天 Bruce 和 Dave 都会在开车上班的路上写机器人代码
We have about a 45-minute drive each day.
我们每天要开车 45 分钟
And we're tired of driving it.
已经有点厌倦开车了
We'd like to get in to our vehicle and hit the switch and have it drive us home, frankly.
我们真正希望的是 上车之后 点击开关 车子会自动开回家
The Hall brothers own a company that makes audio speakers.
Hall 兄弟俩拥有一家制造音响的公司
Bruce runs the daily business,
Bruce 负责日常运营
while Dave tinkers in the shop.
而 Dave 则负责技术
Dave was the engineer and chief designer behind a new robot drive system.
Dave 是工程师和首席设计师 我们的新机器人驾驶系统全靠他
And that enabled us to compete in robot competition, such as BattleBots.
有了这套系统 我们才能参加机器人竞赛 比如 BattleBots
Great. These guys are from Silicon Valley.
非常好 这些家伙来自硅谷
And they mean business. Look at this bad boy. How heavy is that?
他们可不是玩票的 看看这个家伙 他有多重？
350 pounds.
350 磅
We got second place in the world championship in Robot Wars.
我们在 Robot Wars 机器人擂台上获得了全球第二名
If you think about fighting robots where you're actually
战斗机器人需要手工通过远程控制设备
controlling them through a remote control device,
来操控其行为
the next logical step is to have a vehicle that drives itself.
按照这个思路 下一步就是让车辆能够自动驾驶
Instead of lasers, the Hall brothers experimented with video cameras.
Hall 兄弟没有使用激光 而是使用了摄像头
Inspired by the way humans see,
他们的灵感源自人类观察世界的方式
the technique is called stereo vision.
这一技术被取名为立体视觉
On the roof, they mounted two cameras side by side.
在车顶 他们并排安装了两个摄像头
By measuring the lateral shift of specific areas in each image,
通过测量每张图像中具体区域的横向侧移
the robot computes the distance of objects and
机器人可以计算对象距离
creates a difference map to avoid hitting them.
并创建一个分差地图 从而避免撞到它们
Even after decades of research,
经过了数十年的研究后
stereo vision is an unproven technology and at higher speeds,
立体视觉技术仍然不够成熟 速度一旦提升
notoriously unreliable.
就变得非常不可靠
After a few scares,
在几度惊魂之后
the Hall brothers scrapped stereo vision and started building their spinning laser.
Hall 兄弟放弃了立体视觉技术 开始打造旋转激光器
In the fields of Iowa,
爱荷华州的训练场上
Team TerraMax is a group of defense contractors.
我们来看看由国防供应商组成的 TerraMax 团队
Like all competitors, they're not allowed to use
和所有竞赛者一样
government money to compete in the Grand Challenge.
他们不允许使用政府资金来参加机器人挑战大赛
Still, for them, this is no hobby.
但对他们而言 这不是消遣
Their vehicle is a big yellow goose that might lay a giant golden egg.
他们的车辆就像一只黄色的大鹅 或许会下一只巨大的金蛋
TerraMax is a six-wheel drive vehicle.
TerraMax 是一辆六轮驱动车
It is really the logistical backbone of the Marine Corps.
它是海军陆战队物流的中坚力量
And we think it's one of the most mobile vehicles in the world.
我们认为 它是世界上运动性最好的车辆之一
Oshkosh has sold more than 6,000 of these trucks to the military.
Oshkosh 向军方售出了 6,000 多辆这种卡车
With the prowess of an Olympic athlete,
它像无畏的奥运会运动员一样
it plunges into water,
冲入了水中
charges uphills, and even takes to the air.
爬上了山丘 风驰电掣
So, it's got the muscle.
它充满了力量
But what about the brains?
但是不是足够聪明呢？
Without a driver, TerraMax is more of a timid giant than a raging bull.
TerraMax 更像是个温柔的巨人 而不是疯狂的公牛
But the team is confident of its future.
但团队很看好它的未来
In 10 years, the Pentagon plans to convert
五角大楼准备在未来十年里
one third of all military vehicles to unmanned operation,
将三分之一的政府车辆变为无人驾驶的
and Team TerraMax is very eager to help out.
TerraMax 团队对此动力十足
Making autonomous vehicles is a tough problem,
研发无人驾驶车是个大难题
but apparently, not tough enough for Anthony Levandowski,
但对 Anthony Levandowski 来说 似乎还不够难
who is turning the Grand Challenge into a two-wheeled balancing act.
Anthony 把机器人挑战大赛变成了双轮车平衡赛
A bike can do things that a truck and a car really can't do.
自行车能够承担卡车和汽车无法胜任的任务
You can do really sharp turns.
它可以急转弯
You can go through a forest, really tight spaces.
穿越丛林和非常狭促的空间
The agility is just there that's not on other vehicles.
它的敏捷性是固有的 是机动车辆所欠缺的
Anthony dropped out of grad school at
Anthony 从加州大学伯克利分校辍学后
UC Berkeley and spent two years teaching Ghostrider to stay up by itself.
花了两年时间训练 Ghost Rider 站立并保持平衡
We're making a motorcycle the drives itself.
我们想让摩托车能自动驾驶
Like can you get any cooler than that?
还有比这个更酷的吗
That's why everybody on the team puts in so many hours,
团队的每个人都投入了大量时间
because when you see it work,
因为当成功的时候 你肯定
you say, "wow, I made that."
会说 哇 这是我做出来的
A year earlier, at the first Grand Challenge,
一年前 在首次机器人挑战大赛上
Ghostrider made its world debut.
Ghost Rider 在世界舞台上首秀
I haven't slept in two days and I'm super excited.
我两天没有睡觉 超级兴奋
I mean, this is the culmination of six months worth of
我想说的是 这是辛苦奋斗了六个月的成果
work and I forget to turn on the stability.
但我忘记打开平衡了
And then, the second I saw it start to fall and not steer, I said,
但我看到它摔倒的那个霎那 我说
"oh my god, I forgot to switch."
“我的上帝 我忘记打开平衡了”
That's life.
这就是命啊
You know, bad things happen,
福祸难料
but this will never ever happen to me ever again.
但这种事情不会再发生了
The Grand Challenge just basically takes up all of my life.
我这辈子基本上都在为机器人挑战大赛而努力
Like, I don't really talk to my friends anymore.
我不再和朋友聊天
I don't have girlfriend right now.
现在还没有女朋友
I say, I think it's totally worth it though.
但我觉得这完全值得
This could be a chance of a lifetime.
这种机会一生难求
Stanford University is a strong competitor
斯坦福大学是一名强劲的对手
entering the Grand Challenge for the first time.
他们是首次参加机器人挑战大赛
I think the teams did great in the first time round and performed very well,
我觉得参赛团队第一次都做得非常棒
but it was obvious there were some missing links,
但很明显 某个环节出了问题
some missing science to actually win this race.
我们需要科学指导 才能赢得比赛
And these are the challenges I live for.
这是我终生期待的挑战
That's why I do what I do.
是我的使命 为此我义无反顾
For almost eight years,
在过去约 8 年的时间里
Sebastian Thrun was Red Whittaker's colleague at Carnegie Mellon.
Sebastian Thrun 是 Red Whittaker 在卡耐基梅隆大学的同事
They share a passion for robots,
他们都对机器人充满激情
but Thrun has little interest in hardware,
但 Thrun 对硬件没什么兴趣
and convinced Volkswagen to donate a vehicle with steering, brake,
他说服了大众 捐献了一辆带有转向、刹车和
and shift actuators that can be controlled by computer.
换挡致动器的车辆 这辆车可以通过计算机控制
The vehicle's name is Stanley.
这辆车叫 Stanley
So, Stanley is nothing else but Stanford.
取名参考了斯坦福大学
But it also gives the vehicle a personality.
但更像是个人名
We think of the vehicle more and more as an intelligent decision-maker.
我们更倾向于把这辆车看作一名智能决策者
Thrun is a computer scientist with a deep interest in
Thrun 是计算机科学家 对机器学习有着浓厚的兴趣
machine learning and robots with personality are his specialty.
他的专长领域是具有人格的机器人
His robots assist the elderly, conduct museum tours,
他的机器人可以帮助老人、负责博物馆导游
fetch tennis balls, and each one embodies
担任网球球童 通过它们
Thrun's desire to create machines that think.
我们不难看出 Thrun 的目标 就是创造出会思考的机器
Sebastian Thrun is interested in the science of robotics,
Sebastian Thrun 对机器人学很感兴趣
in learning about new techniques that can make
他很热衷于了解哪些新技术能够
robots do fantastically advanced things 10,
让机器人在未来 10 年
20, even 50 years from now.
20 年、甚至 50 年能够做一些非常高级的事情
I guess we've mounted them vertically but we have no data so far, right?
现在我们已经把它们垂直安装好了 但是现在还没有数据 对吧？
And we have no software that can do it?
而且我们没有可以收集数据的软件
Yes.
是的
Okay, so how foolish of us.
好吧 我们这是得有多傻
Compared to the Red team,
和 Red 的团队相比
Stanford is a small group with a single focus on software.
斯坦福团队比较小 他们只关注软件
There's a good number of teams who think
有很多团队
the challenge lies in the hardware and God bless them,
认为硬件才是真正的挑战 上帝保佑他们
it's it's great they're doing this and I know there's hardware challenges.
他们能这么想太好了 我知道还有其他挑战
We from the very beginning pursued
我们从一开始就
a very aggressive timeline to focus almost entirely on software.
制定了非常激进的时间表 我们的关注点基本全在软件上
Stanford uses the same laser hardware as the Red team but they're experimenting with ways
斯坦福团队使用了和 Red 团队相同的激光硬件
to use software to give their robot
但他们正在尝试使用软件
a greater role in making decisions about speed and safety.
让机器人在速度和安全的决策方面发挥更大作用
So in this display, the white area is safe to drive.
在屏幕显示中 白色是安全行驶区域
The red area is unsafe to drive and they gray areas you don't know.
红色是不安全区域 灰色是未知区域
And the robot then just has to steer itself so it stays in the middle
机器人只需要确保在道路中心行驶
of the road and avoids this red stuff as much as possible.
尽可能避开红色区域
To test Stanley's software on the original race course,
为了测试 Stanley 的软件在原始赛道上的表现
the team has traveled to the Mojave Desert where the first Grand Challenge began.
团队来到了莫哈韦沙漠 这是首届机器人挑战大赛的举办地点
Most of Stanley's computer code has been written by Mike Montemerlo,
Stanley 的计算机代码大部分是 Mike Montemerlo 写的
Red Whittaker's former PhD student.
他读博士学位时 曾师从 Red Whitaker
Give me steering and throttle.
给我转向和油门控制
Steering is yours. Throttle. You're going. Great.
转向 OK 油门 OK 非常好
Let's step to 15 now.
现在我们加速到 15
What's the mile marker?
里程显示的是多少
7.28.
7.28
7.3 is the critical place,
7.3 是关键地点
in fact right after this turn over here,
实际上 在这里拐弯之后
the Red team rode off the road and that was its final destination in the race.
Red 团队就偏离了道路 这是他们比赛的终点
That's a very exciting place for us,
看到这个地方我们非常兴奋
it's in many ways a historical place because
可以说 这个地方颇具历史意义
it's the end of the previous Grand Challenge.
这是上次挑战赛的终点
Swerve to the right. Sorry.
右转 抱歉
And we're having a problem.
我们碰到了问题
That's the end of the race for us.
这是我们比赛的终点
Yes. What happened, Mike?
是的 出现了什么问题 Mike？
It just- the long lasers can't see.
测距激光有点问题
They're blind in the corner.
检测不到拐角
We're stuck because of a software bug which we're currently debugging.
出现了软件故障 激光测距卡机了 我们正在调试
So our challenge between April now and October will be to get rid of these bugs.
现在是 4 月 在 10 月的挑战赛之前 我们必须排除这些故障
Unbelievably,
难以置信的是
Stanley faltered in the same place that killed the Red team in the first Grand Challenge.
在首届大奖赛 Red 团队出局的地方 Stanley 也同样碰到了问题
But Thrun is confident about going head-to-head against a team he knows well.
但 Thrun 很有信心 认为他们完全可以和这个熟悉的对手一较长短
The Red team is a seasoned competitor and they have a lot of money,
Red 团队比赛经验丰富 而且资金和
a lot of equipment.
设备都不缺
They have a fantastic team.
他们的团队非常棒
I used to be at Carnegie Mellon,
我曾经在卡耐基梅隆大学就读
I know Red very well, he's an amazing person.
我非常了解 Red 他是个了不起的人
I wouldn't be surprised if the Red team and the Stanford team,
如果 Red 团队和斯坦福团队最终赢得挑战赛 我不会惊讶
and maybe two or three other teams were the big teams in the end.
或许还会有两支其他团队获胜
We'll see. It's a race, it's a true race.
等着看吧 这是场比赛 赛场定输赢
The Red team is teaching its robot to go fast,
Red 团队正在训练机器人
up to 50 miles an hour.
把速度提高到 50 英里每小时
Software guru, Kevin Peterson,
软件大师 Kevin Peterson
has been spending long days and nights improving Sandstorms performance at race pace.
为了改进 Sandstorm 的赛场表现 夜以继日
We've been working on Sandstorm for the last month.
上个月我们都在改进 Sandstorm
I just cut sleep out,
我把睡觉给戒了
it's not that tough.
这并不困难
You get three hours of sleep a day, drink some coffee, you're okay.
每天睡三个小时 喝点咖啡 就这么简单
As robot drives, it has to constantly update it's picture of the terrain ahead.
机器人驾驶时 必须不断更新前方路面图像
The faster it goes, the faster it has to update
行驶速度越快 图像更新
this picture or the terrain just gets on top of it.
频率就要越快 否则就无法判断路面状况
This is easy for humans to do because we can see out 300,
对人类来说 这很简单 因为我们能够看到前面 300
400, 500 feet ahead.
400 或 500 英尺远的地方
But robots have sensors like lasers that operate at fixed ranges 60 feet,
但机器人的传感器 例如激光 只能查看固定的距离 60 英尺
at most 150 feet.
顶多 150 英尺
It's like driving through a fog.
就像在迷雾中开车一样
Each team must lift this fog to win the race.
每个团队都必须揭开迷雾 才能赢得比赛
The Red team's secret weapon is hidden inside the dome on Sandstorm's roof,
Red 团队的秘密武器 隐藏在 Sandstorm 的圆形车顶内部
where a high powered laser is mounted on a device called a gimbal.
那里有一个高功率激光器 安装在常平架上
The gimbal is a motion platform that's a little bit like an animal's neck.
常平架是一个动态平台 有点像动物的脖子
It can point sensors left, right, up,
它可以让传感器向上下左右移动
down in such a way that the pounding motion from the vehicle is smooth.
尽量减缓车辆震荡带来的不利影响
Like binoculars, this special laser can see into the far distance.
就像双筒望远镜一样 这个专用激光可以看到更远的距离
By damping vibration, the gimbal gives it
常平架可以起到减震作用 让激光更稳定
a steady gaze and can point it to follow turns in the road.
而且让激光跟上道路的拐弯
The gimbal mounted laser is unique to the Red team,
安装在常平架上的激光器是 Red 团队的独门武器
which has made several from scratch.
他们从零开始 做了好几台
But it's a fancy piece of hardware that's hard to build and easy to break.
但这件酷炫的设备很难制造 容易损坏
There's been a lot of discussion whether you want to gimbal your sensors.
关于是否需要为传感器安装常平架 我们经过了很多讨论
In fact, we've actually decided against it.
实际上 我们的决定是不需要
We decided against it because we wanted simplicity in the system.
因为我们希望系统简洁一些
Every physical system that moves can break,
所有移动的物理系统都容易损坏
and there's a lot of stuff you can do in software.
而软件的发挥余地则大得多
The Stanford team is putting its hopes in a set of
斯坦福团队则寄希望于
off-the-shelf lasers linked through software to a simple video camera.
现有的激光器 他们通过软件把激光器与视频摄像头相连
The camera can see all the way to the horizon.
摄像头可以一直看到远处的地平线
The trick is to give Stanley some way to distinguish the road in the video image.
关键是要找到一些方法 让 Stanley 可以辨识视频图像中的道路
So this is just one laser. You can see it there steer the vehicle.
这里只是一条激光 你可以看到它在驾驶车辆
Stanley's lasers pinpoint smooth terrain right in front of the vehicle.
Stanley 的激光可以定位车辆正前方的平坦地面
By overlapping the laser and video data,
通过叠加激光和视频数据
Stanley can identify the color of
Stanley 就可以识别
the smooth area and search for it in the rest of the video image.
平坦地面的颜色并在视频图像中寻找这种颜色
The area Stanley believes is safe is now shown in red.
红色部分是 Stanley 认为的安全区域
By matching laser and video data on the fly,
通过不断匹配激光和视频数据
Stanley can adapt to changing road conditions and
Stanley 就可以适应不断变化的路面条件
determine safe driving speeds all by itself.
并自行决定安全的行驶速度
Making a car really intelligent requires to give it an ability to adapt.
要让一辆车真正具备智能 必须让它能够适应环境
It's just like in human life,
就像人类一样
we don't enable kids to have a rule for every contingency.
我们不会给孩子制定每种紧急情况下的行为规则
We tell them how to learn from contingencies
我们会告诉孩子 如何吃一堑长一智
and make them smarter and then we trust them to learn.
我们相信他们的学习能力
Stanford is the only team using adaptive vision to achieve ray speeds.
斯坦福是唯一使用适应性视觉来提升比赛速度的团队
Whether it will work well enough for the Grand Challenge will soon become clear.
这种方法能否应对挑战赛 我们拭目以待
Back at the California Speedway
回到加州高速公路
after more than a year of fevered preparations,
在一年的紧张准备后
the Grand Challenge is on.
机器人挑战大赛揭开了序幕
Officials from DARPA,
来自 国防高等研究计划署
the Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency
DARPA 的官员
are judging the final runs of the qualifying event.
正在观看预赛最后几轮
Forty-three teams are competing for just 20 slots in
一共有 43 支团队
the second and perhaps final Grand Challenge Desert Race.
竞争沙漠挑战大赛第二轮 也许是最后一轮的 20 个席位
After failing three times to complete the two mile obstacle course,
在两英里障碍赛道上 Ghostrider 已经失败了三次
Ghostrider is making its final attempt.
现在是最后一次尝试
It shows surprising agility until it enters the tunnel.
在进入隧道之前 它的敏捷性都令人惊叹
It self-righted. Oops, no.
它站起来了 噢 不
Looking like a wounded animal,
它像一只受伤的动物
it falls down and cannot get up.
跌倒了 没能起来
For Anthony Levandowski, the quest for the Grand Challenge is over.
对 Anthony Levandowski 来说 机器人挑战大赛已经结束了
That was our chance and it was
我们本来有机会的
unfortunate but that's life.
很不幸 但世事无常
Hey DAD! Are we there yet?
嗨 兄弟！ 准备好了吗？
For the Hall brothers,
对 Hall 兄弟来说
it's also the moment of truth.
这也是检验成果的时刻
First obstacle, no problem.
第一个障碍 顺利通过
This is looking good. This is looking solid barring
看起来很好 非常稳健
any hardware issue I think we're going to make it.
如果没有硬件故障 我觉得我们肯定能成
Coming up the other end. At opposite ends of the track,
先跑一小圈 在赛道两端
The brothers Hall hold their breath as
Hall 兄弟屏住呼吸
their new laser sensor guides the truck along the course.
看着他们的新激光传感器引导卡车在赛道上行驶
Alright, let's see if this obstacle detection works.
好的 看看障碍探测功能如何
Here's the test.
挑战就在眼前
Did all the years of work pay off?
这么多年的付出 能否终有所获？
Turn you. Thank you. Right around.
拐弯 拐弯 完美绕过
It's almost as though it was programmed to do that.
和程序设定的几乎完全一样
You're now in the race. You're in the race.
你现在进入正赛了 你进入正赛了
By finishing the course,
跑完赛道后
the Hall brothers have now earned a place in the main event.
Hall 兄弟赢得了正赛的参赛资格
Booyah baby. You've got to love it.
干得漂亮 你会喜欢它的
Ladies and gentlemen, TerraMax.
女士们 先生们 TerraMax
Team TerraMax
TerraMax 团队
also qualifies for the race.
也进入了正赛
Come give me some.
来 来个拥抱
Thank you, Jeff.
谢谢你 Jeff
Sandstorm's first run was not a dainty performance,
Sandstorm 的第一次尝试有点狂野
but after the Red team recalibrates its lasers,
但 Red 团队重新校准了激光之后
the robot loses its appetite for hay.
机器人终于对草堆不感兴趣了
Sandstorm's younger sibling almost failed to make it to the start.
Sandstorm 的年轻兄弟差点没能到达起点
Ten days earlier on a practice run,
十天前 在一次练习中
Highlander swerved sharply and rolled on its roof.
Highlander 大幅摇摆 然后翻车了
For the Red team's prized robot it looked like the end of the rope.
Red 团队非常重视的这台机器人好像到了穷途末路
Lot 25 we've got Highlander in motion.
25 号机器人 Highlander 开始比赛
Miraculously, Highlander is back in action though hardly tested.
尽管几乎没有测试 Highlander 奇迹般地恢复了行动
First barrier.
第一个障碍
It has a shaky start
刚开始还有点不稳
but over the course of three runs,
但赛道跑了三次之后
Highlander clocks the fastest time of any robot at the qualifying.
Highlander 的行驶时间是所有机器人中最快的
That thing's hauling.
它抵达了终点
That's more like it.
这还差不多
A first time competitor Stanley is an unknown quantity.
首次参赛 Stanley 完全是个未知数
No one knows what to expect.
没有人知道它表现如何
The robot passes cleanly through the first gate.
它漂亮地经过了第一扇门
It shows impressive speed on the backstretch,
在非终点直道上 它速度惊人
but it's not as fast as Highlander.
但比 Highlander 要慢一些
Like a proud parent,
Sebastian 就像自豪的父母一样
Sebastian records the moment for posterity.
录下了他的孩子的这一时刻
Yes, so far so good.
一切正常
Flawless.
完美
I don't see he has made a mistake at all. It's perfect.
我没观察到他犯任何错误 太完美了
Aided by adaptive vision,
在适应性视觉的辅助下
Stanley is the only vehicle that
Stanley 成为了第一台
never gets an obstacle.
没有碰到任何障碍的车辆
In 36 hours, the race,
在 36 个小时后
the real Grand Challenge will begin.
真正的机器人挑战大赛即将开始
DARPA announces who qualified and what the starting order will be.
DARPA 宣布参赛选手和车辆顺序
Highlander is number one on Saturday morning.
Highlander 是 1 号 时间为周六上午
Stanford number two on the pole position.
斯坦福 是 2号
And number three, Sandstorm.
3 号 Sandstorm
The race course is a circular maze that zigzags for
赛道是一个圆形迷宫 道路曲折
132 miles across the Mojave desert near the outskirts of Las Vegas.
共 132 英里 横穿拉斯维加斯市郊附近的莫哈韦沙漠
It's mostly flat but rough and unpaved.
地面平坦 但有点起伏 没有铺砌
It includes tunnels, cattle gates,
赛道包括隧道、牛栏门
and steep mountain switchbacks.
和陡峭的之字山路
With a 10-hour time limit,
限时 10 个小时
the race will demand speed, agility,
因此选手必须速度、敏捷和
and endurance that no machine has ever demonstrated on its own.
耐力兼备 这对机器而言是前所未有的挑战
The exact route is a deeply guarded secret.
准确的道路仍是未知之谜
But now, at 4:00 am on race day it's released to the team.
但在比赛当天凌晨 4 点 消息传到了参赛团队
On a compact disc is a road map defined by 2900 GPS waypoints.
在一张光盘上 记录了一张道路地图 全程有 2900 个 GPS 路点
All your hopes and dreams are on this disc.
你们所有的希望和梦想 都靠这张光盘了
Teams have two hours to analyze
参赛团队有两个小时 来分析地图
the map and plug it into their robots before the race begins.
并在比赛开始之前 把数据导入机器人
In several minutes, the Stanford team loads the course into their robot.
几分钟后 斯坦福团队把赛道导入了机器人
Stanley will choose its own speeds on the fly,
Stanley 会根据不同地形
adapting to different types of terrain.
自行动态调节
The red team takes a far different approach.
Red 团队采取的方式完全不同
Concealed in their trailer,
他们躲在房车里
Whittaker's troops look like they're planning an attack.
就像一支等待出征的军队
The race course is layered on top of
他们把赛道信息单独成层 添加到
elevation data and satellite images stored in the red team's computers.
电脑中存储的海拔信息和卫星图像上方
The route is broken into sections and distributed
道路被分为不同区段
to team members who will examine it in minute detail.
分发给团队成员 仔细检查细节
Thousands of waypoints are added to fill gaps in DARPA's map,
他们在 DARPA 的地图上添加了数千个路点
and each point can be adjusted to optimize the robot's path.
每个点都可以进行调整 优化机器人路径
Speeds are set for every inch of terrain.
他们为每个地点设定了速度
Right where you are.
就在这里
Right where you are. Just zoom, zoom, zoom.
就在这里 放大 放大 放大
Red believes his robots must have
Red 相信 机器人必须拥有
as much information as possible to gain the winning edge.
尽可能多的信息 这样能增加赢面
That preference is to air in the direction of overkill.
我们觉得 怎么准备都不会过度
I wouldn't want to reflect Sunday morning that we lowballed it
我可不想在周日早上懊悔 没有多标记一些数据
It is slow. It is flat. It is.
这里比较慢 这里是平的 对的
On a course that appears easy,
在这条看似简单的赛道上
Red makes a critical decision.
Red 做了个关键决定
So here is the punch line.
我们的策略是这样的
He decides to run Highlander at a fast and risky pace.
他决定让 Highlander 冒险一些 快速行驶
Sandstorm will be the tortoise.
Sandstorm 则会扮演乌龟
In the parking lot.
在停车场
Running 40 minutes slower in the hope that at least one red team robot will finish.
比 Highlander 慢 40分钟 这样至少有一台机器人会到达终点
The first time it's ever been done, autonomous vehicles.
这是无人驾驶车的历史性时刻
As dawn breaks over the desert,
当黎明破晓时分
robots prepare to boldly go where no robot has ever gone before.
机器人像勇士一般 准备进行一场前所未有的探险
Vehicles will be launched at five-minute intervals and race against the clock.
车辆启动间隔为 5 分钟 比赛时间分别计算
as you can see, there will be an audible phone.
你可以看到 车上装了收听电话
Hey, Red.
你好 Red
All the best.
祝你好运
Hey.
嗨
Very fun. Very good day.
很有趣 天气不错
And we have auto-ball.
我们安装了音响警报器
Highlander leads the pack followed by Stanley and Sandstorm.
Highlander 首先出发 后面是 Stanley 和 Sandstorm
And we have moving from Stanley.
Stanley 也开动了
Ladies and gentlemen. The start of the DARPA Grand Challenge
女士们 先生们 DARPA 机器人挑战大赛开始
The cheering teams are now spectators.
团队成员只能像观众一样鼓掌加油
Their work is done. After months of tireless efforts, there's a lot at stake.
他们的工作已经完成 在几个月不知疲倦的努力后 他们来到了关键时刻
And now Sandstorm.
现在是 Sandstorm
A vision they all shared will now be put to the test.
今天 就是见证他们共同梦想的时刻
You go.You go. You go.
加油 加油 加油
Highlander, Stanley, and Sandstorm.
Highlander、Stanley 和 Sandstorm
During the first eight miles of the race.
在前 8 英里的路程中
Highlander gains two minutes on Stanley.
Highlander 比 Stanley 快了两分钟
At times, the Stanford robot
有时候 斯坦福的机器人
seems confused and disoriented.
似乎有点困惑 分不清方向
Sandstorm is keeping pace with Stanley, five minutes behind.
Sandstorm 和 Stanley 速度一致 落后 5 分钟
Launch of the sixth spot here. There. Are we there yet?
现在轮到了 6 号 好的 准备好了吗？
It will take two hours to launch all the robots.
所有机器人都出发需要两个小时
Each one leaves the chute with confidence.
所有机器人启程时都信心满满
A far cry from the first Grand Challenge with many faltering within sight
这和第一次挑战大赛截然不同 当时很多机器人
of a start and no robot went beyond seven miles.
在起点犹豫不前 没有机器人跑过七英里
The start of the race is pretty cool.
比赛开始很不错
It was really exciting to see all the robots go.
看着这么多机器人出发 真让人兴奋
I was excited and apprehensive.
我很兴奋 但同时
at the same time. You just don't know what's going to happen with a robot.
也有点紧张 我们不知道机器人的表现究竟如何
It was entirely out of our hands.
这完全不在我们的控制范围内
Far from the crowd,
在远离人群的地方
Highlander now leads a fleet of driver-less machine racing the clock across the desert.
Highlander 现在带领着一群无人驾驶机器 穿越沙漠 和时间赛跑
Team DAD has passed two robots,
Team DAD 超了两台机器人
and is now heading to the front of the pack.
现在正向第一名发起冲击
Eight team robots have now passed the seven mile mark that ended the last race.
已经有 18 台机器人超过了 7 英里标志 这是上次比赛达到的最远点
Miraculously, the great team from New Orleans is holding its own,
值得赞叹的是 来自新奥尔良的 GRAY 团队守住了位置
only weeks after the city was destroyed by hurricane Katrina.
几周前 卡特里娜飓风袭击了这座城市
TerraMax was the last to start and brings up the rear.
TerraMax 最后一个出发 负责殿后
Following each robot, DARPA chase vehicles relay information back to the start.
DARPA 的跟踪车辆跟着每台机器人 把信息传回赛道起点
Here, teams gather around DARPA's displays.
在这里 各团队聚集在 DARPA 的显示屏前
That's just pretty sweet. Throwing away in the front.
这太棒了 我们正在领跑
For throwing.
正在领跑
For now.
现在
We're pulling away from DAD.
我们拉开了和 DAD 的距离？
No, from Stanford.
不 是和斯坦福的距离
30 miles into the race,
在赛道的第 30 英里处
Highlander is making time on Stanley.
Highlander 正在拉开对 Stanley 的时间优势
Behind Stanley, Sandstorm is closing the gap and may pass the Stanford robot.
在 Stanley 后面 Sandstorm 正在紧追 有可能超车
behind them, robots are starting to drop like flies.
在它们后面 机器人开始零散掉队
At mile 26, team DAD's laser comes unbolted from the roof.
在第 26 英里处 DAD 的激光从车顶上脱落
Officials in the chase car hit the kill switch,
追踪车上的官员按下了结束开关
and for the Hall brothers,
Hall 兄弟的
the race is over.
比赛结束了
At a media stop,
在媒体站
a group of journalists sees Highlander charging toward them in the distance.
一群记者看到 Highlander 从远处向他们冲来
Highlander seemed to come down the hill very smartly.
Highlander 下坡的时候似乎很聪明
But then, as it started to mount the next hill,
但是开始攀爬下个山坡时
it looked like it ran out of gas,
看上去好像汽油不足
or the engine cut off,
或者发动机停了
or somebody in there threw it into neutral.
或者有人调成了空档
It just stopped moving and slid back down to the bottom of the hill.
它停了下来 然后往后滑回了山坡底部
Something was wrong with Highlander,
Highlander 出了问题
and it did not have its normal get up and go.
它不能正常启动和前进了
Highlander keeps on rolling but cannot maintain its intended pace.
Highlander 仍在前进 但没法维持预定速度
Red and the team slowly realize that things are not going according to plan.
Red 和他的团队逐渐意识到 情况可能脱离了计划范围
I don't know whats going on with Highlander, it's weird.
我不知道 Highlander 发生了什么事情 这很奇怪
It's running slow.
它现在很慢
It's running real slow.
特别慢
Highlander struggles to summon the power to complete its mission.
Highlander 正在努力挣扎 想要完成比赛
Behind it, Stanley is rapidly approaching.
在它后方 Stanley 正在迅速接近
But Highlander recovers on the flats,
但 Highlander 在平地上恢复了正常
and for many miles they continue neck and neck.
在接下来很长的距离中 这两台车齐头并进
One hundred and two miles into the race,
比赛进行到第 102 英里
Stanley's video camera records a milestone event.
Stanley 的视频摄像头录下了标识性的时刻
Stanley has passed Highlander.
Stanley 超过了 Highlander
At that point, we pretty much knew Highlander wasn't going to win the race,
当时我们非常肯定 Highlander 赢不了比赛了
we thought Sandstorm might have a chance.
我们认为 Sandstorm 可能会有机会
It was really disappointing.
我们非常失望
Five hours after leaving the starting line,
离开起点 5 个小时后
Stanely now leads the pack and just five robots remain on the course.
Stanley 现在处于领先 赛道上仅剩 5 台机器人
To finish, they must wind through a treacherous mountain pass
要完成比赛 它们必须经过一条蜿蜒崎岖的危险山道
and Stanley has now make life or death decisions.
Stanley 现在的每个决策 都将决定它的生死
Somehow, Highlander has managed to reach the summit of the pass,
在没人注意的情况下 Highlander 成功到达山道顶端
but the gimbal is turned sideways and appears to be dead.
但它的常平架翻向了一侧 似乎坏了
Without its secret weapon,
没有了秘密武器
must rely on short range lasers and GPS to avoid disaster.
它只能依赖于近程激光发射器和 GPS 才能避免灾难的发生
Right behind Highlander, Sandstorm is in good shape but driving slowly according to plan.
在 Highlander 后方就是 Sandstorm 它一切良好 正在按计划缓慢行驶
The crowd gathers.
人们聚集到了一起
A blue dot appears in the distance.
远处出现了一个蓝点
Yeah! Stanley!
耶！ Stanley！
After driving six hours and 53 minutes,
行驶 6 小时 53 分钟后
at an average speed of 90 miles an hour,
以 19 英里每小时的平均速度
Stanley is about to become the first vehicle in history to drive
Stanley 即将成为史上第一台
132 miles by itself.
无人驾驶 132 英里的汽车
Bot 25. Red team, two.
25 号机器人 Red 团队 2 号车
Highlander from this Pittsburgh PA,
Highlander 来自宾夕法尼亚州匹兹堡的
Carnegie Mellon University,
卡内基梅隆大学
the red team two is an alliance.
Red 团队车队的 2 号车
21 minutes behind Stanley,
落后 Stanley 21 分钟
Highlander limps to the finish.
但 Highlander 坚持到了终点
Minutes later, the trusty veteran appears
几分钟后 备受信赖的老兵出现在大家的视野中
Bot number19.
19 号机器人
It was just amazing to see this community of people.
能够看到这群人真是太棒
That community succeeded today.
他们今天成功了
Behind me, there are three robots that made it all the way through
在我后面 有三台机器人也穿越了沙漠
the desert and all three of them did the unthinkable.
它们都完成了不可思议的壮举
It's such a fantastic success for this community.
对这个群体来说 这是一次伟大的胜利
I think we all win.
胜利属于所有人
Before announcing the winner,
在宣布获胜者之前
DARPA officials honor the five finishing teams.
DARPA 官员宣布 5 支完成比赛的队伍
TerraMax is fifth.
TerraMax 是第 5 名
A dark horse,
一匹黑马
the Gray Team from New Orleans, is fourth.
来自新奥尔良市的 Gray 团队 获得第 4 名
Highlander is third.
Highlander 是第 3 名
Sandstorm, Whittaker's tortoise,
Whitaker 团队的乌龟 Sandstorm
was just 11 minutes behind the winner.
仅落后冠军 11 分钟
So, I guess it's time.
最后 冠军时刻
The check goes to Stanley.
百万美元支票获得者是 Stanley
So, someone from Stanley will please come up here.
有请 Stanley 团队成员上前
What Stanford did in
斯坦福在如此
a short span of time is amazing in the robotics world.
短的时间内所取得的成绩 是机器人学的骄傲
On this scale of time to develop a system this sophisticated that can navigate
在这么段的期限内 开发出一套如此复杂的系统
so well over such a wide variety of terrain at such high speeds,
能够以如此高速穿越如此复杂的地形
it really is worth its place in the history books.
这个成绩 值得历史铭记
The source of Highlander's problems remains
Highlander 的问题原因仍不清楚
a mystery that may have been the result of its rollover.
可能是因为之前翻过一次车
The engine pump, the only thing that was
发动机问题 唯一的原因是
short was not having a top end speed on the gas pedal.
我们油门没有提供最高速度
Except for that, ran like a charm.
除此以外 一切都很完美
This really was like a horse race.
这就像赛马一样
It finished in such close times.
抵达终点的时间非常接近
So, the red team is justifiably proud for having both of its robots finished the course.
Red 团队足以自豪 他们的两台机器人都完成了比赛
Many believe the completion of the Grand Challenge is
很多人坚信 这次挑战大赛
a giant step that will push robots out of the lab and into the real world.
是机器人学的一大步 它足以让机器人走出实验室 进入应用阶段
The forces that will make this happen are embodied in the passion and vision of true men.
这个伟大成绩的实现 依赖于两个人的激情和梦想
The world needs both Sebastian Thrun's and Red Whittaker's.
感谢 Sebastian Thrun 和 Brent Whitaker 的贡献
If robotics is ever going to become part of the daily fabric of our lives,
如果要机器人真正成为人类生活的一部分
it needs those scientists who can come up with those far out
我们需要科学家们能够高瞻远瞩
ideas for how machines are actually going to start to think,
思考机器人如何才能具备思维和推理能力
to reason and it also needs the builders,
此外 我们还需要建造者、实施者
the implementers, and those who are driven to make things work in the real world.
以及将科学在实验室外落地的实干家们
There is every reason to believe all those who
我们完全有理由相信
participated will continue their quest to innovate even
尽管这次挑战大赛已经成为历史
though the Grand Challenge itself is now history.
所有参加了比赛的人仍会努力探索创新
What about the future?
那么 未来会怎样？
Will mechanical warriors take over the battlefield?
机械战士会接管战场吗？
Will we all be passengers on the highways of tomorrow?
未来的高速公路上 是否会彻底实现无人驾驶？
Someday, the great robot race may well be remembered as a moment when
总有一天 人们会想起这场伟大的机器人比赛
the partnership between humans and the machines we create was forever changed.
这场比赛 彻底改变了人类和人类所创造的机器之间的关系
On NOVA's website, get behind-the-scenes outtakes,
欢迎访问 NOVA 网站 了解幕后花絮
showing teams as they prepared for The Great Robot Race.
和参赛团队准备这场机器人挑战大赛的详细内容
Find it on pbs.org.
请访问 pbs.org
To order this show or any other NOVA program for 19.95 plus shipping and handling,
订购本节目或任意其他 NOVA 节目 只需 19.95 美元 包括邮费和手续费
call WGBH Boston video at
你也可以呼叫波士顿美国公共电台 (WGBH) 视频中心
1-800-255-9424.
号码为 1-800-255-9424
NOVA is a production of WGBH Boston.
Nova 由波士顿美国公共电台 (WGBH)制作